Finding aid for Richard Nims papers, 1880s-1990s
Bentley Historical Library
Richard Nims papers
1880s-1990s
1937-1954
Bentley Historical Library
Nims, Richard, 1917-1994
2010155 Aa 2; UAm
2.6 linear feet
1 oversize folder
Detroit-born, amateur photographer and Navy veteran who graduated from the University of Michigan in 1941. Nims' photographs document student life in Ann Arbor during the late 1930s, with particular focus on the popular student hangout The Pretzel Bell; and life in the Navy and the South Pacific during 1944-1945 and 1951-1952. The collection consists primarily of photographs and negative with some mixed material such as diaries, newspaper clippings, correspondence and ephemera.
The collection was donated in June 2010 by Kirk Nims (donor number 10376 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Richard Nims was born in Detroit, Michigan on August 28, 1917. He was the second child of Claude Henry Nims and Agnes Christine Klagstad. He had an older brother Paul Theodore Nims. When Richard was 18 months old, his mother died after giving birth to her third child. The baby also died. With his father not able to care for his two sons, he split them up to live with relatives. His mother's sister, Thora Emilie Klagstad Jones, became Richard's caretaker. Richard lived with his Aunt Thora in Toledo, Ohio until he was four years old, at which time he moved back to Detroit to live with his father and brother.
After graduated from Eastern High School in Detroit, Richard moved to Ann Arbor to attend college at the University of Michigan. His brother Paul was already a student at Michigan by the time Richard began classes in the Fall of 1934. While in Ann Arbor, Richard was employed as a student manager and accountant at the popular student hangout the Pretzel Bell Tavern. The Pretzel Bell opened in 1934 just shortly after the repeal of Prohibition. The Pretzel Bell, located at 120 E. Liberty Street, was a few blocks west of Ann Arbor's dry line. During this time, any establishment east of Division Street was prohibited to sell liquor. Therefore, students wanting to buy a drink would have to venture to establishments located outside Ann Arbor's dry territory like the Pretzel Bell. "The P-Bell," as it was commonly known, quickly became a popular, co-educational social center. At one point during his time in Ann Arbor, Richard lived in an apartment above the restaurant.
On February 9, 1940, Richard married Margaret Alice Perry, the only child of Raymond Alvin Perry and Florence Hattie Bos. The couple married at the First Congregational Church on S. State Street and E. William Street in Ann Arbor. Over a year after their marriage, Richard graduated from University of Michigan with an A.B. degree in Economics.
After graduation, Richard took a job with Michigan Alkali Company in Wyandotte, Michigan. On September 19, 1943, the couple had their first child, Eric Nims. Soon after the birth of their son, Richard entered the Naval Officers Training School in Chicago. He graduated from the program as a Lieutenant, Junior Grade and a navigator.
In 1944, Richard was assigned to Landing Craft Support (Large) stationed in the South Pacific. While with his company, Richard acted as the photographer, documenting action at sea, life aboard a warship, scenery of the South Pacific, and street scenes in the Philippines and Tokyo during 1944 and 1945.
When his naval duty ended, Richard returned to Michigan and worked at Wyandotte Chemical Corp. On June 25, 1949, Margaret and Richard had their second child, Kirk Nims, in Wyandotte, Michigan.
In 1951, Richard was again called to serve in the South Pacific for the Korean War. Richard was stationed on the USS Corson (AVP-37). Richard again acted as ship photographer during this second tour of duty. He was discharged from the Navy as a full Lieutenant.
Richard spent his remaining years living in Michigan with his family. He died on September 28, 1994.
The collection consists primarily of photographs and negative taken by Richard Nims with some mixed material such as diaries, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and ephemera. The collection contains the following series: Photographs/Negatives, Other Papers, and Motion Pictures.
Wyandotte (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Japan.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Mackinac Island (Mich.); Manistique (Mich.); Philippines.; Streets -- Japan -- Nagasaki.; Streets -- Japan -- Tokyo.; Streets -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Streets -- Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Pacific Area.; Wyandotte (Mich.); Contact sheets.; Diaries.; DVDs.; Identification cards.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; School yearbooks.; Stereoscopic photographs.; Stereoscopes.; Boy Scouts of America.; Nims, Richard, 1917-1994.; United States. Navy.; University of Michigan -- Students -- 1931-1940.; Nims, Richard, 1917-1994.; Pretzel Bell (Tavern: Ann Arbor, Mich.); United States. Navy.; University of Michigan.; University of Michigan -- Football.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1931-1940.; Wyandotte Chemical Corporation.
- Photographs/Negatives
  The series Photographs/Negatives is made up of four subseries: Ann Arbor, Navy, Family and Friends, and Other.
  - Ann Arbor
    The subseries Ann Arbor contains photographs taken by Richard Nims while a student at the University of Michigan. The photographs document student life and Ann Arbor street scenes during the late 1930s. The subseries contains many images of the popular student hangout The Pretzel Bell; the images are primarily interior shots showing patrons eating and drink and staff members at work. The images from the "Ann Arbor Album" are not prints but rather contact sheets; however, there is a negative for every image.
    - Ann Arbor Album
      - November 1936-January 1937, 2 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 1-2)
        (Liberty Street, Nickels Arcade, Burton Memorial Tower under construction, the Pretzel Bell)
      - February 1937, 2 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 3-4)
        (Pretzel Bell, drive-in movie theater screening Swing Time, college friends hanging out in a house located at 344 S. Division)
      - March 1937, 2 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 5, 10)
        (Pretzel Bell, columns of Angell Hall Idiot's Delight playing at the Cass Theatre in Detroit)
      - April 1937, 4 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 6-9)
        (Pretzel Bell, students on campus, reading room in an unidentified library, ice arena, State Street, Liberty Street, train station, lecture hall)
      - May 1937, 4 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 11-14)
        (track field, baseball field, professor lecturing, State Street, canoeing on an unidentified lake, UM campus, students sitting on the steps of Angell Hall, Pretzel Bell, Burton Memorial Tower)
      - June 1937, 2 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 15-16)
        (Angell Hall, Peony Garden in Nichols Arboretum)
      - July 1937 (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 17)
        (countryside outside of Ann Arbor, Pretzel Bell)
      - August-October 1937, 4 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 18-21)
        (Pretzel Bell, UM Football Stadium, Soapbox Derby, Detroit Ballroom Eastwood Gardens)
      - November 1937, 2 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 22-23)
        (UM Football Stadium, State Street)
      - December 1937, 3 folders (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 24-26)
        (UM campus, Pretzel Bell)
      - January 1938 (Box 1)
        (roll film no. 27)
        (Pretzel Bell, Burton Memorial Tower, Liberty Street)
      - Prints and Miscellaneous Ephemera, 1937 (Box 1)
    - College Friends, snapshots, circa 1937 (Box 1)
    - NACA Dinner, 1948 (Box 1)
    - The Pretzel Bell, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
      (5 prints; all interior shots)
    - UM Campus, circa 1937 (Box 1)
      (3 prints; includes images of Diagonal Walk, Law School, and Angell Hall.)
    - UM Football Stadium
      - Unidentified Game, circa 1937 (Box 1)
        (4 prints)
      - Michigan-Ohio State Football Game, 1943 (Box 1)
        (contact sheet; includes images of Eric Nims as a newborn)
  - Navy
    The subseries Navy is made up of photographs and negatives taken by Richard Nims during his two tours in the South Pacific in 1944-1945 and 1951-1952. The folder titles for images dated 1944-1945 come from a descriptive list complied by someone other than Richard Nims. The descriptive list can be found in the folder titled "Line Ceremonies." The images capture life aboard a warship, battles at scene, scenery of the South Pacific, and street scenes in the Philippines and Tokyo.
    - Naval Officers Training School (Chicago, IL), 1944 (Box 1)
      (see also oversize class photo of 18th class U.S. Naval Reserve Midshipmen's School, May 10, 1944 in oversize folder UAm)
    - Landing Craft Support (Large), circa 1944 (Folder UAm)
    - Line ceremonies, circa 1944-1945 (Box 1)
      (includes descriptive list of photographs)
    - In support of a landing; "Remains of the destroyer Halligan," (Okinawa), circa 1944-1945; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - The Philippine Liberation Ribbon; "San Pedro Bay anchorage, Leyte Gulf," Osmeña Beach,", 1944-1945; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - The Occupation of the Japanese Empire; "Tokyo Bay," "The Break Buddha of Kamakura," "Nagasaki--after the bomb,", circa 1944-1945; 6 folders (Box 1)
    - USS Corson AVP-37 and Okinawa, 1951; 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Post-war life in Japan, circa 1945-1951 (Box 1)
    - Warships at sea, circa 1945-1951; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Life aboard ship and on naval base, circa 1945-1951 (Box 1)
    - Naval ceremony on, circa 1952 (Box 1)
    - Towing Exercise, 1952 (Box 1)
    - USNS General Simon B. Buckner (T-AP-123), 1964 (Box 1)
  - Family and Friends
    The subseries Family and Friends includes photographs not taken by Richard Nims, such as childhood pictures of Richard with his mother and brother. Richard Nims' childhood photographs provide a strong portrait of growing up in Michigan during the late 1910s and early 1920s. Most of the Family and Friends photographs are casual snapshots rather than formal portraits of various people related to Richard and Margaret Nims.
    - Agnes Klagstad and family, 1880s-1910s; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Claude Henry Nims, 1920s-1960s (Box 2)
    - Eric and Kirk Nims, 1940s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Margaret Alice Perry Nims, 1910s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Misc. Snapshots, 1910s-1950s; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Perry, Bos, and Johnstone family, 1880s-1950s; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Richard Nims, 1910s-1990s; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Other
    The Subseries Other consists of miscellaneous images of Michigan with the exception of photographs from a trip Richard Nims took to Boston in 1937. The majority of the snapshots are from holiday celebrations or family trips around the state.
    - Boston (Red Sox game, skyline, Bunker Hill Monument, circa 1937 (Box 2)
    - Camp Brady (Waterford, Mich.), circa 1930s (Box 2)
    - Color-stereo slides of nudes (with stereo viewer), circa 1950s (Box 2)
      (29 slides)
    - Couple sitting on deck of the Mackinac Island Ferry, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Christmas Parade, circa 1949 (Box 2)
    - Locations outside of Ann Arbor, circa 1930s (Box 2)
      (includes photograph of W.K. Kellogg Auditorium in Battle Creek, Mich.)
    - Ludington, Mich., 1956 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Sovereign Consistory, Valley of Detroit, composite group photo of members, May 1918 (Folder UAm)
    - "Off to War,", 1951 (Box 2)
    - Snapshots of students in a classroom, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Soap Box Derby, Rouge Park (Box 2)
    - The Wabash Cannon Ball Train, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Wyandotte Chemicals Corporation
      - Office Christmas Party, circa 1947 (Box 2)
      - South Plant Accounting Department, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Wyandotte, Mich.
      - Fourth of July Parade, 1944; 1949 (Box 2)
      - Centennial Celebration, 1954 (Box 3)
- Other Papers
  The series Other Papers provides a context for the visual material contained in the Photograph/Negatives series. The series is made up of diaries, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and ephemera. There are two diaries in the series including a Boy Scouts of America diary kept by Richard Nims when he was 13 years old; and another diary kept by Margaret and Richard Nims documenting their first year of marriage. This newlywed diary makes many references to Ann Arbor's Pretzel Bell.
  - Agnes Klagstad's Lecture Notebook, circa 1910s (Box 3)
  - Claude Henry Nims
    - Correspondence and Misc. Papers, 1953-1982; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Published Writings, 1960-1967 (Box 3)
  - First Year of Marriage Diary of Richard and Margaret Nims, 1940 (Box 3)
  - The Pretzel Bell, news clippings and menu, 1974-1985 (Box 3)
  - Richard Nims
    - Academic Transcripts, 1941; 1954 (Box 3)
      (University of Michigan and Wayne State)
    - Background Information, 1965; 2010 (Box 3)
    - Boy Scouts of America, Troop 91 (Detroit, Mich.)
      - Diary, 1930 (Box 3)
      - Membership Certificates, 1934; 1938 (Box 3)
    - Eastern High School Yearbook (Detroit, Mich.), 1934 (Box 3)
    - Identification and Membership cards, 1940s-1968 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan Student Identification, 1937-1941 (Box 3)
    - USNR Orders, 1943-1944 (Box 3)
    - USS Corson (AVP-37) and USS Markah (AD-21), Ephemera and Naval booklets, 1944-1952 (Box 3)
  - Wyandotte, Mich. Centennial, Program and Publication, 1954 (Box 3)
- Motion pictures, circa 1950s; 8 mm
  The Motion Pictures are home movies of trips to Mackinac Island, Manistique, and downtown Detroit, probably in the early 1950s. The films, made by Paul Klagstad, an uncle of Nims, are in color and silent. DVD use copies have been made.
  - Straits of Mackinaw and Mackinac Island, Michigan (Box 3)
  - Detroit, Michigan (Box 3)
  - Manistique, Michigan (Box 3)